Alessandro B. Melchiorre

@ alessandro.b.mel@gmail.com · ♠ karapostK · ♦ karapostk.github.io · 🛅 a-melchiorre

Experience

Graduate Researcher

Johannes Kepler Universität Linz

September 2019 - Ongoing

Linz, AT

Research focus on Recommender Systems, Explainable and Fair AI/ML.

- Developed a novel effective recommendation algorithm and a tool to offer explainable predictions and model's insights.
- Devised a new approach for modular debiasing of latent embeddings of pre-trained ML recommendation models.
- Led 2 funded science-communication projects that resulted in interactive exhibits for thousands of people.

Visiting Student

Technische Universität Berlin

September 2018 - February 2019

Berlin, DE

- Awarded 1 of 12 departmental merit-based scholarships
- Developed a SQL query resolution system for Geo-distributed federated databases while enforcing data shipment constraints. Implemented in Java and Apache Calcite.

Selected Publications

Full list is available at karapostk.github.io/publications

- A. B. Melchiorre, S. Masoudian, D. Kumar, M. Schedl, Modular Debiasing of Latent User Representations in Prototype-based Recommender Systems, Paper at European Conference on Machine Learning (ECML PKDD) 2024
- A. B. Melchiorre, C. Ganhör, N. Rekabsaz, M. Schedl, ProtoMF: Prototype-based Matrix Factorization for Effective and Explainable Recommendations, Paper at ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (RecSys) 2022
- D. Afchar*, A. B. Melchiorre*, M. Schedl, R. Hennequin, E. V. Epure, M. Moussallam, Explainability in Music Recommender Systems, Article in AI Magazine 2022 - Deezer Collaboration
- A. B. Melchiorre, N. Rekabsaz, E. Parada-Cabaleiro, S. Brandl, O. Lesota, M. Schedl, Investigating Gender Fairness of Recommendation Algorithms in the Music Domain, Journal in Information Processing & Management 2021
- A. B. Melchiorre*, V. Praher*, M. Schedl, G. Widmer, LEMONS: ${\bf Listenable\ Explanations\ for\ Music\ recOmmeNder\ Systems}, Demo$ Paper at European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR) 2021

Selected Projects

- Hassaku: Recommender System framework in Python/PyTorch. Implements all ML steps from data processing to logging.
- ProtoMF: Explainable and effective recommendation algorithm based on interpretable user/item prototypes.

Referees

Prof. Markus Schedl (supervisor) Johannes Kepler University Linz Full Professor markus.schedl@jku.at

Navid Rekabsaz (ex-colleague) Thomson Reuters AI Labs Senior Applied ML Scientist navid.rekabsaz@gmail.com

Summary

Machine Learning researcher with a Computer Science background. I enjoy carefully developing each project aspect, from data processing to model predictions, to deliver effective and well-structured solutions on time.

Skills

//> Programming Languages

Python, SQL, Java (Proficient) C/C++, JavaScript (Familiar)

Software

PyTorch, NumPy, pandas, Ray Tune, scikit-learn, matplotlib, git, Jupyter, Weight&Biases, bash Spark, Keras, TensorFlow, Hadoop, Kafka, Apache Calcite (Previous Experience)

AE Languages

Italian (Native), English (Fluent), German (Beginner)

Funded Projects

See karapostk.github.io/projects for more info

Black Holes of Popularity

PI role

62.000 EUR

February 2022 - September 2022 ₩11 people Project coordination and planning, recruiting, role assignments, and fostering ideas and contributions.

Emotion-aware Music Tower Blocks

Co-PI role

54.000 EUR

February 2021 - September 2021 ♣9 people System design, data analysis, tasks assignment, API integration development. In Python and JavaScript.

Education

PhD in Computer Science/AI

Johannes Kepler Universität Linz

September 2019 - Ongoing (Expected End 2024) Focus on developing and designing (music) recommender systems, with emphasis on explainability and fairness.

MSc in Engineering in Computer Science

Sapienza Università di Roma

September 2016 - February 2019 Graduated with honors.

Rome, IT

Machine Learning (Python, TensorFlow), Big Data (Hadoop, Spark), Natural Language Processing

BSc in Engineering in Computer Science

Università degli Studi di Napoli Federico II

September 2013 - June 2016

Naples, IT

Graduated with honors.

Software Engineering (UML, Design, Analysis, Testing), Computer Programming (C, C++, Java), Databases (SQL, DBMS)